<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Best | Key Shift in Cmd]]></title>
  <link href="http://greena13.github.io/blog/categories/best/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://greena13.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-08-02T21:11:23+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://greena13.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aleck Greenham]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Best Still Untitled: The Adam Savage Podcast Episodes]]></title>
    <link href="http://greena13.github.io/blog/2016/07/02/the-best-still-untitled-the-adam-savage-podcast-episodes/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-02T20:45:47+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://greena13.github.io/blog/2016/07/02/the-best-still-untitled-the-adam-savage-podcast-episodes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Still Untitled: The Adam Savage podcast was one of the very first that I got into. Its conversational style and the fact that Adam regular answers listeners' questions makes for a welcoming and engaging listening experience.</p>

<p>Like many long-running, lightly produced podcasts, however, Still Untitled has touched on a great many subjects - some much more interesting than others. Here is a list of my favourite episodes, broken down into two categories.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Actionable Advice for Creative Work</h2>

<p>Many of these have very similar titles as they involve Adam answering questions from the Tested.com and maker community at large. There is some great advice and inspiration to be found in many of these episodes for creative work. Like <a href="http://greena13.github.io/blog/2016/06/25/the-best-tim-ferriss-show-podcast-episodes/">my Tim Ferriss Podcast recommendations</a>, I would suggest having a pen and paper handy in case you feel the need to take notes.</p>

<p>They are roughly grouped by theme and are not in chronological order, so be prepared to have to listen to five minutes or so of non-sequential preamble at the start of many episodes.</p>

<ul>
<li>Work ethic</li>
<li>Autodidacticism</li>
<li>Getting started making</li>
<li>Where to find stuff</li>
<li>Research tips</li>
<li>Scrounging, buying, finding materials</li>
<li>Skeptics</li>
<li>Shop storage schemes</li>
<li>Questions!</li>
<li>Your questions answered</li>
<li>Building an inexpensive toolkit for beginners</li>
<li>Etsy questions answered</li>
<li>Questions and answers</li>
<li>More questions!</li>
</ul>


<h2>Interesting Stories</h2>

<p>In addition to having a lot of knowledge to impart, Adam has lead a very interesting life. These episodes were particularly engaging stories from his past.</p>

<p>Listen when you want to be enthralled in a good, short story by a cool story or two.</p>

<ul>
<li>Video Games</li>
<li>Practical special effects</li>
<li>Adam&rsquo;s land cruiser</li>
<li>Flying in a U2</li>
<li>Tales of adventure</li>
<li>The significance of billiards</li>
<li>Rainy days</li>
</ul>


<h3>Related</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="/blog/2016/06/25/the-best-tim-ferriss-show-podcast-episodes">The Best Tim Ferriss Show Podcast Episodes</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Best Tim Ferriss Show Podcast Episodes]]></title>
    <link href="http://greena13.github.io/blog/2016/06/25/the-best-tim-ferriss-show-podcast-episodes/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-25T13:37:11+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://greena13.github.io/blog/2016/06/25/the-best-tim-ferriss-show-podcast-episodes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have been needing an easy way of recommending episodes of the fantastic Tim Ferriss Show podcast for a while now. What follows is a list of the episodes I found the most value in.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>You can see the entire episode list on <a href="http://fourhourworkweek.com/podcast/">the podcast&rsquo;s website</a>.</p>

<p>The easiest way of listening to the episodes is to either go to the <a href="http://fourhourworkweek.com/podcast/">website</a> and search the episode titles or search on your favourite podcast app. Google will work, also.</p>

<p>Episodes are in the <em>approximate</em> order of strength of recommendation.</p>

<h2>Highly Actionable</h2>

<p>These podcasts are Tim talking to his audience, often answering up-voted questions or short verbal essays on a particular subject. They are generally shorter and immediately useful and actionable. Pausing and taking notes is highly recommended.</p>

<h3>Personal Focus</h3>

<ul>
<li>How to 10X Your Results, One Tiny Tweak at a Time</li>
<li>The 9 Habits to Stop Now — The Not-To-Do List 
Productivity” Tricks for the Neurotic, Manic-Depressive, and Crazy (Like Me) </li>
<li>5 Morning Rituals That Help Me Win The Day</li>
<li>What I’d Add To The 4-Hour Workweek for 2015 (And Much More)</li>
<li>How to Avoid the Busy Trap (and Other Misuses of Your Time)</li>
<li>Drunk Dialing Fans–Celebrating The 100th Podcast Episode!</li>
<li>25 Great Things I Learned from Podcast Guests in 2015</li>
<li>On Zero-to-Hero Transformations</li>
<li>The Unusual Books That Shaped Billionaires, Mega-Bestselling Authors, and Other Prodigies</li>
</ul>


<h3>Professional Focus</h3>

<ul>
<li>How Creatives should negotiate</li>
<li>Should You Start a ‘Startup’ or Build a Cash-Flow Business?</li>
<li>How to Build a Large Audience From Scratch (And More)</li>
<li>How to Build a World-Class Network in Record Time</li>
<li>The 5 Things I Did To Become a Better Investor</li>
</ul>


<h2>Guests - Actionable Advice</h2>

<p>These episodes are Tim interviewing guests, or guests answering listeners' questions. Generally they are much longer, and with more space between useful takeaways, but the podcast guests remain interesting or entertaining throughout. Note taking is encouraged, but not essential.</p>

<ul>
<li>Scott Adams: The Man Behind Dilbert</li>
<li>Derek Sivers on Developing Confidence, Finding Happiness, and Saying “No” to Millions</li>
<li>Derek Sivers Reloaded – On Success Habits and Billionaires with Perfect Abs</li>
<li>Ed Cooke, Grandmaster of Memory, on Mental Performance, Imagination, and Productive Mischief</li>
<li>Episode 2: JOSH WAITZKIN</li>
<li>What Evernote’s Phil Libin Learned from Jeff Bezos, Reid Hoffman, and Others</li>
<li>How One Computer Hacker Conquered Online Dating, Opens Locked Cars, and More</li>
<li>The Tim Ferriss Show: Interview with Peter Thiel, Billionaire Investor and Company Creator</li>
<li>The Tim Ferriss Show, Episode 18: James Altucher on How to Say “No”, Fail Better, and Build Businesses</li>
</ul>


<h2>Guests - Interesting People and Careers</h2>

<p>These interviews are with usually highly visible and always interesting people. Listen when you wish to be entertained and engaged, but don&rsquo;t necessarily want to have some useful takeaways.</p>

<ul>
<li>Tim Ferriss Interviews Arnold Schwarzenegger on Psychological Warfare (And Much More)</li>
<li>Jamie Foxx on Workout Routines, Success Habits, and Untold Hollywood Stories</li>
<li>The Tim Ferriss Show: Interview of Kevin Kelly, Co-Founder of WIRED, Polymath, - Most Interesting Man In The World?</li>
<li>Kevin Kelly on Artificial Intelligence and Designer Babies</li>
<li>Marc Goodman, FBI Futurist, on High-Tech Crime and How to Protect Yourself</li>
<li>Dissecting the success of Malcom Gladwell</li>
<li>Meet “Scorpion,” The Real-Life Santa Claus</li>
<li>The Tim Ferriss Show, Episode 22: Ed Catmull, President of Pixar, on Steve Jobs, Stories, and Lessons Learned</li>
<li>Tony Robbins on Morning Routines, Peak Performance, and Mastering Money</li>
<li>The Maverick of Brain Optimization</li>
<li>The Rags to Riches Philosopher: Bryan Johnson’s Path to $800 Million</li>
<li>How Facebook’s #30 Employee Quickly Built 4 Businesses and Gained 40 Pounds with Weight Training</li>
<li>Will MacAskill on Effective Altruism, Y Combinator, and Artificial Intelligence</li>
<li>Matt Mullenweg on Polyphasic Sleep, Tequila, and Building Billion-Dollar Companies</li>
<li>General Stan McChrystal on Anti-War Americans, Pushing Your Limits, and The - Three Military Tests You Should Take</li>
<li>The Tim Ferriss Podcast, Ep 15: Neil Strauss, Author of The Game</li>
</ul>


<h3>Related</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="/blog/2016/07/02/the-best-still-untitled-the-adam-savage-podcast-episodes">The Best Still Untitled: The Adam Savage Podcast Episodes</a></li>
<li><a href="/blog/2015/02/13/how-to-start-a-startup-notes">Notes on how to start a startup</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
